<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>LZX Technical Manual Blog</title>
        <link>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog</link>
        <description>LZX Technical Manual Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modular Submodules]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/modular-submodules</link>
            <guid>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/modular-submodules</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[September flew right past us here at LZX, with steady (if tedious) progress toward Chromagnon production on my end, and multiple longer term production projects wrapping up in the workshop.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>September flew right past us here at LZX, with steady (if tedious) progress toward Chromagnon production on my end, and multiple longer term production projects wrapping up in the workshop.</p>
<p>During spring cleaning earlier this year, we uncovered our remaining stock of Vidiot specific production parts, such as enclosures and side panels.  Rather than sending them to the junk, we've been making progress over the Sumer on building up a limited batch of 24 units using those parts.  You can order one now at <a href="https://lzxindustries.net/products/vidiot" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://lzxindustries.net/products/vidiot</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/vidiot-f78c26636acedb582e5250d1d2d970a8.png" width="480" height="270" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We've made some revisions to our Double Vision system bundle -- including a full 3U EuroRack enclosure using our new sync and power distribution board architecture.  This version also includes the TBC2 expander, in lieu a DC Distro.  We have a couple systems in stock right now for purchse: at <a href="https://lzxindustries.net/products/double-vision-system" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://lzxindustries.net/products/double-vision-system</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/double-vision-94e0122ed94973695ca8ed6f704f28ac.png" width="480" height="270" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>On the Chromagnon front, I have been laser focused (pun intended) on preparing the hardware for production.  After this last prototype review, the full context is a lot easier to see, including the remaining steps needed until we're actually placing the order for production core boards and molded parts. This process has been grueling, as the core board's BOM and parts count are massive. Thus, I've been breaking some repetitive parts of the analog circuit into submodules.</p>
<p>The first of those submodules is a four quadrant multiplier sub-assembly that encapsulates our discrete design. This design is based on topologies in classic multiplier ICs such as MC1494 and MC1495, which are long obsolete.  A core requirement of the Chromagnon design is the implementation of this discrete multiplier, as there are over 20 of them in its analog circuit!  We've been working on this circuit since before Chromagnon was even conceived, and after so many revisions I'm very pleased with how it is performing.  Here's a look at the submodule.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/submodule-5044199d99470952d22aa4fe9987c5c1.png" width="480" height="265" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This submodule is being reintegrated into Chromagnon's core board, which reduces the BOM count by a few hundred parts and will allow pre-testing/calibration of the analog circuit. We have already received our initial order of these submodules and are testing them now.</p>
<p>Revisions to Chromagnon Core RevH will be ordered by the end of this week.  I'm not used to spending entire weeks on a single PCB layout, so that gives you an idea of the scale of the effort required to push this forward. This is the first version of the board that is being 100% assembled out of our workshop, which means we're priming it to be ready to go, and it is a candidate for production.  I'd love to have it all confirmed and initial quantities ordered by the end of October -- there's not a lot left to stand in our way of that happening.</p>
<p>And now, here are answers to the questions you have submitted since the last update:</p>
<p><strong>Marty asked, "Looking forward to shipping on Chromagnon. Well done on all the work so far. When shipping does occur. Will the cost of the unit, detailed for customs. Reflect the date of purchase or current value? I'm just worried about the extra tax I'm going to pay when it ships to Australia."</strong></p>
<p>Hi, Marty. The customs info will reflect the price you paid on your original sales invoice.</p>
<p><strong>Pat asked, "Can we expect Chromagnon unit #1 to ship out by Halloween?"</strong></p>
<p>Probably not, Pat!  In the next Chromagnon milestone, I'm hoping to be telling you we've got RevH confirmed and have ordered initial production parts. That is getting very close, and would mean we have unit #1 here. Whether or not it's shipping by that date, I don't know -- firmware is about 95% done, but there's still a few items to wrap up and test once the hardware is sealed.</p>
<p><strong>Paul asked, "Would it be possible to demonstrate through your LZX documentation learning program, the placement and attachment of modules into a Vessel or eurorack case? And if any modules have to be linked together or sync. This is for those who don’t know. Thank you."</strong></p>
<p>Hi Paul. Yes, certainly! We do have a basic guide to doing this on our website at <a href="https://lzxindustries.net/getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://lzxindustries.net/getting-started</a>. However, I'd love to expand on that and have some videos and better photos to go along with it.</p>
<p>Until next time,
Lars</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Chromagnon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Light At The End]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/light-at-the-end</link>
            <guid>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/light-at-the-end</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I hope everyone has enjoyed their Summers and is looking forward to the Fall.  For me, this time of year has always meant getting ready to learn, whether that was in my prior career in e-learning development, with my kids starting the next grade, or in my own educational goals. This year it will mean entering a period of content creation for LZX-- documentation, videos, tutorials, and any other resources that serve your own learning and creative pursuits in making video art.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I hope everyone has enjoyed their Summers and is looking forward to the Fall.  For me, this time of year has always meant getting ready to learn, whether that was in my prior career in e-learning development, with my kids starting the next grade, or in my own educational goals. This year it will mean entering a period of content creation for LZX-- documentation, videos, tutorials, and any other resources that serve your own learning and creative pursuits in making video art.</p>
<p>Last week we reached a couple of big Chromagnon milestones: The RevG Core hardware has been fully reviewed; slow scan raster generation for ILDA laser and low-bandwidth displays has been implemented; and we have a complete synthesizer on the workbench -- finally!  Unlike software based visual generators, or simpler analog circuits (like our modules), Chromagnon is a design that has been very difficult to show as a work in progress until all of the pieces, both hardware and firmware, were in play.  I am very glad to be at this point, because you'll no longer have to take my word for it when it comes to what, how, and why Chromagnon does what it does.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vhlNyixE1vo?si=Vl5htKHzqpl1NEQK" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"></iframe>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/testing-3539a2e8cdd4dafe65b65dc648b8dc5b.png" width="480" height="364" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Testing in progress.  Excuse the clutter!</p>
<p>I'll be recording more in September, including a walk through of Chromagnon's user interface and functions, as we continue checking off items on our test list and working towards finalization of the design for production.</p>
<p>Since our last update, we have one new user question.</p>
<p>** Pete said "Hi, Lars! Glad to hear your progress update, it must feel pretty good to get out of the cave and into the light!  I'm curious as to what h/w you have chosen for the Chromagnon. I'm interested in FPGAs and have ordered a Zybo board to experiment with." **</p>
<p>Pete, thanks for writing!  Chromagnon's hardware is quite intensive.  At it's core, it is an analog synthesizer with a fully analog, wideband signal path -- but also, there is a complex digital embedded system which handles the user interface, video input decoding and scaling (SD to HD and HD to SD), and 10-bit ramp waveform generation.</p>
<p>For the digital system, we are using a System-on-Module from MYiR, which you can read more about here. This is based on the Xilinx Zynq system on chip -- the same as employed on your Zybo board.  Xilinx FPGAs are used heavily in broadcast and imaging applications of all kinds. On our host board, we use video encoding and decoding interface ICs such as the ADV7181C, ADV7123 and ADV7125 for interfacing analog video with the Zynq IO ports. I hope you have fun with the Zybo board!</p>
<p>Talk to you again soon,
Lars</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Chromagnon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Code Cave]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/code-cave</link>
            <guid>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/code-cave</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Over the past several weeks I have been writing Chromagnon’s firmware, and I’m happy to say that I now have a complete version ready for testing.  I wanted to reach this milestone before I wrote a new blog, as it represents my exit from the Code Cave and back into the workshop.  So let my eyeballs readjust – this blog will mostly be about the software.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the past several weeks I have been writing Chromagnon’s firmware, and I’m happy to say that I now have a complete version ready for testing.  I wanted to reach this milestone before I wrote a new blog, as it represents my exit from the Code Cave and back into the workshop.  So let my eyeballs readjust – this blog will mostly be about the software.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/chromagnon-e23b2c0c52bf78d09f10230b703a5f9a.png" width="480" height="400" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><em>My trusty Chromagnon RevG development unit, back at the test bench</em></p>
<p>From Memory Palace and TBC2 to Chromagnon, I have needed to double down on my embedded software skills. Approaching these instruments, I had many firmware and software projects behind me – but none at this level of structural complexity.  So I was surprised by the scale of what I still needed to learn with regards to architectural patterns and systems level design. Hardware scales easily – five circuits is five circuits – but in software, writing a state control system for five asynchronous modules is a different beast entirely.  The experience has definitely kindled a love for embedded development with modern C++ in general, and I look forward to doing more of it. During the past few weeks of getting cozy with Chromagnon’s digital brain, I felt both confident and effective, and that was a relief.</p>
<p>What’s next? With firmware in place, we are able to move into a new verification process for the instrument as a whole.  That’s a long list of tests, including nearly 200 different video input conversion modes – in addition to all combinations of Chromagnon’s 12 compositor modes, 3 chroma modes, 3 luma modes, and 4 primary modes. Most of this testing has already been done with prior versions of the hardware, but we still need to repeat the tests now that we have a firmware candidate. In the next blog, I’ll describe how that’s going.</p>
<p>In other news, we have added the DIY kit version of our power &amp; sync distribution busboard to the webstore.  Check that out here.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/sync-c1b31073f87827f1f18cfd06304d2d49.png" width="480" height="480" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We also have a restock of Scrolls hitting the shelf. While I have not had time to film it yet, here is a script for a video about Scrolls that you may read.</p>
<p>Our Summer sale is active, with discounts offered on Sum/Dist, Contour and Matte modules.</p>
<p>We're still taking orders for Double Vision systems. It has been exciting to watch new video artists dig into the depths of their systems over the Summer.</p>
<p>Here are your questions, since the last post.</p>
<p><strong>Luis asked, "Are there any plans to further improve the Memory Palace firmware?"</strong></p>
<p>Memory Palace Mk2 will be a follow-up project after Chromagnon. The first phase of that project will include some revisions to the existing Mk1 firmware, as our plan is to support concurrent versions. The main difference being that Mk2 will support HD modes.</p>
<p><strong>Mat asked, "Just curious about the timeframe in regards to the Double Vision preorder. Will there be a long wait? I just ordered recently and will hopefully not have to wait as long as I have for the Chromagnon."</strong></p>
<p>Since we launched the Double Vision system bundle, the average wait time for a shipment has been about 3 weeks.  I expect that to stay consistent.  We have a good flow coming thru the workshop of stocking the module sets in small batches. Your Double Vision is actually in QC today, and planning to ship tomorrow.  You sent in this question on July 15th, so that seems pretty consistent with the average lead time.</p>
<p><strong>Thomas asked, "Are preorders for the Chromagnon still open? Nothing happens when I press the preorder button, and I see people selling their preorder slots online.  Am I too late to buy one?"</strong></p>
<p>Preorders are open. If you click the preorder button on the product page, you should see it added to your shopping cart (but the site doesn't automatically take you there.)  This is not a limited edition -- the date we have Chromagnons in stock and all preorders are fulfilled is still uncertain, but you don't need to worry about missing out.  We hope to keep the instrument in production for many years.</p>
<p><strong>Patrick said, "It seems like a lot is happening over there right now, and there are many updates and things to discuss in each monthly journal post. Is there any inclination to get back to doing a weekly journal post to keep us more in the loop? Or would that slow production down because it's another thing to think about? Either way, I'm glad Chromagnon is still being worked on. Since June has come and gone, is there any new estimate for when the first unit might ship out?"</strong></p>
<p>Patrick, I'm sorry the updates have been less frequent.  Currently the core team is down to myself full time and three part timers.  Writing these blog posts is no huge burden, but it does take 2-3 hours out of my work week each time. With hardware development and workshop projects, tasks are shorter -- 1 to 16 hrs each -- to do a board layout, or revision, or build a prototype.  With software or circuit design it's often 3-6 week sprints, during which it can be difficult for me to do anything but write code or run simulations.  With code sprints in the rear window for now, I'll try to up the pace of the updates.  I'm hoping to be past hardware verification and on to production and user docs soon.</p>
<p><strong>Kazys asked, "How effective is Chromagnon with a Vectrex? Can it do Rutt-Etra style rescanning into X / Y / Z out of the box?"</strong></p>
<p>We have not recorded any Vectrex monitor tests yet, and that should be the final judge of this -- but you've got the right idea. The scaler decimation settings allow you to output low frequency rasters for lower bandwidth displays, like laser projectors and the Vectrex. I expect some of the middle settings to be right for use with the Vectrex -- a raster size of 120x68, for example.</p>
<p><strong>Kazys also asked, "If I have a Chromagnon, why would I need an ESG3? Is it still useful?"</strong></p>
<p>Definitely. Chromagnon has no dedicated RGB level or offset controls, so ESG3 would add a lot, with each of ESG3's six knobs and three switches representing parameters not present on Chromagnon.  Another reason to have an ESG3 is if you are using Chromagnon in the context of a modular system, and want to mix it's output with other sources before the final output.</p>
<p>If you have questions about hardware development, software development, LZX, or you just need someone to talk to, write to me here:  <a href="https://wkf.ms/47lhPPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://wkf.ms/47lhPPA</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Lars</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Chromagnon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Summer Crunch]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/summer-crunch</link>
            <guid>https://docs.lzxindustries.net/blog/summer-crunch</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Dear video friends,]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear video friends,</p>
<p>June has seen a lot of projects landing at the workshop and some significant pushes in firmware development. Over the Spring we have transitioned into outsourcing SMT assembly of our modules in smaller batches, in an effort to keep things stocked and flowing, and those efforts are running smoothly.</p>
<p>The Summer is traditionally a period of low sales for us, so we have decided to open a sale for some modules we have lots of stock of. You will find Contour, Matte, and Sum/Dist have been marked down 25%, for the time being, on our webstore. If you've been wanting to pick one of these up, now is a good time to do so.</p>
<p>Here is a summary of notable recent milestones:</p>
<p>TBC2 1.0.3 firmware was released.  This includes better support for the VGA input expander and the addition of a 240p input mode.  So pull out your SNES and Chrono Trigger cartridge if you want to travel thru time, saving the world from Lavos, while also traveling thru your analog video circuits.</p>
<p>If you had an outstanding order for the TBC2 VGA input expander module, it has been shipped.</p>
<p>We are now stocking fan upgrade kits for TBC2 Mk1 &amp; Mk2 on our webstore.  If you already ordered the Mk1 (Orion style) kits from us, we neglected to send mounting screws in the first few shipments -- but the screws have already been mailed to you in a separate package this week.  So look out for that.</p>
<p>Memory Palace 2.0.2 firmware was released.  This is a maintenance release which includes a screensaver function to prevent burn-in on your OLED screen in the case that you are logging lots of hours on your device.</p>
<p>TBC2's video engine firmware has been ported to Chromagnon and is running on the new RevG PCB assembly.  I've put a lot of time into merging work from TBC2 into a common library that is now shared with Chromagnon, to ensure consistent performance across both devices.  This will also set the stage for Memory Palace Mk2 revisions, which will be the big project after Chromagnon development has wrapped.</p>
<p>This past week I have written a parameter state engine, with auto recovery from loss of power or corrupted backups, to use across our firmware for various modules.  This will ensure that Chromagnon boots back up in the same state in which it was powered down. We'll be able to integrate that functionality into the next firmware release for TBC2 as well.</p>
<p>Entering July, I am still investing most of my time into Chromagnon firmware and hardware review.  This includes writing tests for validating the control assemblies we've already built and the RevG hardware.  Currently I am improving the software that allows for firmware update from MicroSD card, since with Chromagnon it needs to run in a headless manner. (Unlike TBC2 and Memory Palace, which both used OLED screens and keypads.)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/thermal-camera-d44ea4d7f072ebf343c1cb51a0c9322b.png" width="480" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><em>Chromagnon RevG under the thermal camera!</em></p>
<p>A few background projects landed in June as well, including some parts we will use to revise the Cadet DIY series.  This maintenance revision will be ongoing for a few months, and will bring the core DIY modules up to spec for HD video synthesis timing, and offer some new supply chain/build options for hard to source components.  Once these revisions are complete, we'll offer the PCB and frontpanel sets again via our webstore.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/thonk-cadets-51bd12756080fdf0ea98f98925c9063a.png" width="480" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Our order from Thonk for parts to use in building Cadet revisions.</p>
<p>In our ongoing initiative to offer a line of professional enclosures for our modules, the pieces for a 3U variant of our 6U rackmount case have arrived.  These will be an upgrade option for your Double Vision system, and we'll soon offer a version of the Double Vision system which uses this case.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://docs.lzxindustries.net/assets/images/case-3u-1c9404300d162ca25a11b4a45e35d153.png" width="480" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>3U variant of our powered EuroRack case for video synthesizers</p>
<p>Additionally, a kit variant of our 10 amp DC power and sync distribution bus has arrived, for DIY installations into other cases. This version includes a chassis-mounted DC input jack and screw terminals on the PCB.  The busboard is equivalent to three times the amount of power and number of connectors as our 4HP DC distro module, and it will be suitable for powering cases of Gen3 modules over 252HP.   Look for this on our webstore in July.</p>
<p>Next case projects will include a portable variant with a lid, and a legacy power supply expander for the 6U and portable cases.  The legacy power supply expander will be perfect for powering audio modules or older generations of LZX modules using the new Vessel cases.  I'm excited to have a case that works with everything.</p>
<p><strong>Pat asked "The prototypes for the plastic pieces and enclosure look great! I’m stoked that you guys have come this far with the project!. A few weeks ago you said you are hoping to ship unit one in June, is that still the plan?"</strong></p>
<p>Hi, Pat. Thanks!! We are getting close to that point. The Summer slump I mentioned slowed us down slightly -- and I squeezed in the TBC2 and Memory Palace updates that folks have been waiting on for a while, which delayed us as well. With the firmware project above wrapped up, we will be close to shipping the first unit.  Then we can roll up our sleeves and get our headspace shifted into rolling into a rhythm with the remaining Chromagnon production, documentation, and fulfillment.</p>
<p><strong>Yuya said "Thank you so much to Lars and all of you who continue to work hard every day towards the launch of Chromagnon! I love Memory Palace. Luckily my Memory Palace display hasn't burned in yet, but I'm super nervous about it happening... Are there plans to release a new firmware that implements a screensaver like TBC2? Also, are there any plans to release a fan upgrade kit like TBC2? Thank you again!"</strong></p>
<p>Hello, Yuya. Thank you so much for your enthusiasm and support.  It is a relief on my stress levels and a boon to the projects we are working on to hear from you all like this.  As you can read above, the Memory Palace firmware update should help with your concerns about screen burn in.  I will definitely add a fan upgrade kit for Memory Palace to our project queue, now that TBC2 kits are out the door.</p>
<p>Got more questions, suggestions, comments or high fives? Go for it here: <a href="https://wkf.ms/47lhPPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://wkf.ms/47lhPPA</a></p>
<p>I am curious what user documentation projects you would like to see us tackle before the end of the year.  I want to know what would add the most value to your experience with LZX modules you already have. So if you have suggestions, please write to us.</p>
<p>Thanks for tuning in,
Lars</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Chromagnon</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>